<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dinis Peixoto</title>
    <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dinis Peixoto</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dinispeixoto.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Force Python to release memory</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/force-python-to-release-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/force-python-to-release-memory/</guid>
      <description>Let me start by clarifying that there are far better solutions to manage Python&amp;rsquo;s memory other than the one I&amp;rsquo;ll showcase here. The solution/workaround that I will present was appropriate for the problem I was facing, which included having to process multiple really large pickle objects. Please note that loading multiple of these objects to memory was not even an option as they could take up to 20 Gs of memory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A year&#39;s worth of learnings from adopting Mob programming</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/posts/2020/12/a-years-worth-of-learnings-from-adopting-mob-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/posts/2020/12/a-years-worth-of-learnings-from-adopting-mob-programming/</guid>
      <description>At FARFETCH, teams are encouraged to try new development methodologies so that they can deliver even better results while also improving productivity. As a fairly new team, we have continuously been looking for different methodologies that best fit our needs, such as avoiding knowledge silos or a slow-paced reviewing process. Although not every approach that we have tried has worked, the ones that did are now part of our daily development workflow and play a key role in the outcome of the tasks that we deliver.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git Add Patch</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/git-add-patch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/git-add-patch/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s always fun when you find something entirely new, especially when it&amp;rsquo;s a quirk/feature on a tool that you use daily. This time around, I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing about git, in particular an option that you can use when stagging content for your next commit.
Most of the times, I either use git add &amp;lt;file&amp;gt; or if I&amp;rsquo;m sure that every unstaged change should be stagged, git add . will do the job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Not Track - HTTP header</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/do-not-track/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/do-not-track/</guid>
      <description>While I was setting up Google Analytics for this website, something that should be straightforward as Hugo already provides an internal template for this, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that my requests were not being tracked and displayed on the Google Analytics dashboard.
I started by making sure that the internal template was actually being properly used and then, just in case, that the tracking id was correct. Both seemed to be ok.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hey there! 👋</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m Dinis Peixoto, a software engineer based in Braga, Portugal. 🇵🇹 I have been working at FARFETCH (an e-commerce luxury platform 👠) for over 2 years now.
I consider myself an eager to learn person, always with a learn-by-doing philosophy in mind. Other than that, I really like to feel challenged as it enables me to not only learn new things but also improve my problem solving skills.
I truly believe that teaching is one of the best ways to learn, that&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;m currently mentoring csharp and python at exercism.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>