<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>machine learning on Dinis Peixoto</title>
    <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in machine learning on Dinis Peixoto</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dinispeixoto.com/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Distributed model inference using Spark</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/distributed-model-inference-spark/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/til/distributed-model-inference-spark/</guid>
      <description>During the past few days, I have been working on running batch inference for a large amount of data using Spark. The goal was to generate embeddings:
text embeddings using a fine-tuned BERT model image embeddings using a fine-tuned ViT model I will use this TIL to share some of the key learnings I could get from this experience.
Pandas UDF vs Spark UDF Pandas UDF instead of Spark UDF helps improve performance, also allows running in batches of rows/partition instead of a single row/partition (everything&amp;rsquo;s explained here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brand Recommendations - TF-IDF</title>
      <link>https://dinispeixoto.com/posts/brand-recommendations-tf-idf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dinispeixoto.com/posts/brand-recommendations-tf-idf/</guid>
      <description>I have been trying to learn Machine Learning for quite some time now. The main motivation for this was the fact that, at FARFETCH, I work really close to a data science team and wanted to get a grasp of the main challenges that they have to face on a daily basis.
It all started with a couple online courses. The thing with these courses is that you get to learn a lot of cool stuff supported with step-by-step tutorials, but I never took some time to actually build something on my own, that tackles a real issue that I&amp;rsquo;m facing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
